Hey everyone and thanks for jumping back
into the macroverse.
Today we're going to talk about the most
recent labor market report and many of
the mixed signals that we got. We're
going to try to decipher what's actually
going on and why the market is having a
hard time understanding what the Fed is
going to do next. If you guys like the
content, make sure you subscribe to the
channel, give the video a thumbs up, and
check out the sale on ITCremium at
intothecryptoverse.com
where you can get access to these charts
as many as well as many of the
dashboards that we're going to show if
you would like to follow along. I don't
really talk about the macro as much, but
we check in with it about once a month
or so. Um, and then as a reminder, as
always, we do have the ITC conference
coming up here. uh in just a few months
and ticket prices will be going up on
September 1st. So, make sure you guys
get your ticket if you would like to
attend. Let's go ahead and jump in. So,
we're going to start with the total
non-farm payroll because expectations
were completely missed. I believe we
were expecting like 80,000. We actually
came in at 23,000.
Now, historically, when this starts
going down
over a longer period of time, it can
indicate a contraction. Now, sometimes
you'll have down months, for instance,
like you know, July to August of 1997,
and it's not necessarily a contraction,
right? So, that's why we said it needs
to be a durable drop where non-fin
payroll continues to drop. If you go
zoom in over here, you can see that it's
been generally trending up with some
down months. And so what I would
encourage us to do is to first of all,
we can go look at the month-over-month
change. And what you'll notice is that
there there, you know, back in 2021,
2022, 2023, and 2024, there were really
no negative month overmonth changes.
It wasn't until 2025 where we first got
one. And then you can see later in 2025,
we started to get a few more and it's
just been picking up, right? So clearly
there is some weakening there. Clearly
because 2021,
no negative months in terms of total
non-farm payroll. Now we're getting
them. Now, if you look at it quarter
over quarter, it kind of cleans up some
of that. And so when you're looking if
you're looking month over month any
given month and can be negative just
because of some random event quarter
over quarter now you're comparing you
know to several months before you're
going to have fewer sort of false flags.
And in this case you can see it didn't
go negative until about late 2025. Now
where it gets really interesting is when
you look at the year-over-year change.
When you look at the year overyear
change of total non-farm payroll
historically when it goes negative
it's been a recession.
It has not gone negative. Right? So if
you're like well why are we not in a
recession if it's negative? It's not
negative. It was negative for the month
not for the year. Now, if you zoom in,
it was pretty close to going negative
earlier this year, back in February, but
you can see that it bounced up a little
bit. Now, if you look at a percentage
change, just to kind of put this in
terms to where we can really understand
it. Back in 2022,
the employment level was growing total
non-farm growing 5% a year. So even
though things felt bad and some people
said it was a recession because we had
two consecutive quarters of negative
GDP, that wasn't really supported by
what's actually going on in the labor
market. And furthermore,
one of those quarters of negative GDP
was eventually revised upwards, I
believe. So it ended up not even being
two negative quarters of GDP in a row.
When you look at the labor market, you
can see we're adding we were adding 5%
to total non-fin payroll basically every
month. Four to 5%. But you can see that
that has changed. Look how we go through
2023, it weakened. You get into 2024, it
then was at 1% less than 1%. Now we're
basically at 2%. So effectively,
there's basically no net job creation
going on right now. Very there's a
little bit, but it's very, very small.
And so what that means is that there's
not a lot of margin for error. If the
Fed were to misstep at any point in the
coming months, coming year or two, it
could easily turn this negative.
Easily. Now again, a negative non-farm
payroll print does not automatically
mean the stock market has to drop 50%.
Just because the stock market dropped
50% in 2008 and 2001 doesn't mean that
every recession has been like that.
There's been plenty of recessions where
you just had 20% drops, 30% drops, which
can always happen. And if you're an
investor here and you're constantly
worried about that, you shouldn't be
here is is is essentially what I'm
trying to say, right? Any good investor
that stays investing for a long enough
period of time will experience those
draw downs. You just will like I've
accepted it a long time ago for for
years and years and years. I've just DCA
low expense ratio index funds as as far
as the stock market goes. I don't know
what's going to happen but when I buy
them I'm not buying them for tomorrow.
I'm buying them for 20 years from now.
Okay. So that's kind of how I think
about it. In the short term, things can
always be scary, but that's why they
call it climbing the wall of worry. This
is not negative yet, but again, there's
not a lot of margin for error. So then
you would expect that we had a negative
non-farm payroll print.
Therefore, it would stand to reason that
the unemployment rate would have gone
up, right? would make sense. But no, the
unemployment rate continued to drop and
now it's actually dropped from 4.5% last
November all the way down to 4.1%.
So it's gone down4%
basically over the last 7 8 9 months or
so. How can that be? How can you have
fewer draw fewer jobs
but yet the unemployment rate is going
down? You would expect that to not
really make a lot of sense. But one of
the main reasons, not the only reason,
but one of the main reasons that the
unemployment rate went down despite the
fact that we lost jobs is if you look at
the labor force participation rate,
you'll notice that that's also been
falling off a cliff. So, it is true that
you don't have as many jobs,
but there's also not as many people
looking for a job. If you're unemployed
and you're not looking for a job, you
don't count as in the unemployed
statistic.
What the unemployed statistic is looking
at is how many people are out of a job
but want a job. If you don't want a job,
it's not going to count you. So, the
labor force participation rate since
November has dropped from 62.5%
down to 61.4%.
So, more than a full percentage drop in
the labor force participation rate,
which kind of helps explain why the
unemployment rate has been trending down
despite there being some weakness in the
labor market. Now, the weakness in the
labor market is not coming from layoffs.
Now, you've probably seen some headlines
about some pretty big layoffs, but
there's always layoffs in every economy.
Even when things are going incredibly,
incredibly well, there are still
layoffs. There's always layoffs because
there's always businesses that are that
are going bankrupt, there's always uh
businesses that are um restructuring.
There's also just people that get laid
off for whatever reason. There's always
layoffs no matter what. And what you'll
notice is that while layoffs have been
trending up, we're basically just at
pre- pandemic levels, right? Like this
would not suggest recessionary territory
right now. You can see what happens in a
recession. It really goes up. We haven't
had that, right? We've just gotten back
to the prepandemic levels. Now, if you
don't trust this, you can also go look
at something like initial claims.
When you look at initial claims, initial
claims a few weeks ago just printed the
lowest level in in a long time, like
189,000.
The last time it was that low was
probably 50 years ago.
So, a lot of companies aren't really
laying people off right now. They're
just not. Maybe because they saw what
happened in the pandemic where it was
hard to find the right people and they
just don't want to do that. But we have
not entered into that feedback loop of
layoffs leading to less demand which
lead to then more layoffs. We are we are
not in that right now. So layoffs are
low. Initial claims are low. So then
what is it? What do we mean when we say
there's some weakness in the labor
market? Well, we already covered one of
them. Total non-farm payroll was
negative and it's not that far away from
going negative year-over-year.
If you look at job openings,
that one has mostly been trending down,
but recently it showed a little bit of
resilience. This last month it it
trended down.
If you look at
the total temporary cell um what was it?
I think it was the the help services
total temporary help services. That one
had been trending down for a long time.
It started trending back up recently.
So, there's some pockets of weakness and
pockets of strength. Now, some
industries feel like they're like in the
the deepest bare market that you can
imagine, right? Like, think about the
altcoin market. I mean, like, you know,
the altcoin market
has, you know, I mean, look, every
single day there's bankruptcies
basically. I mean, I see a new post on
Twitter. Yeah. And it's Twitter to me
every day. Basically, there's a new
company going under. So there are pro
you could argue in some industries
they're already feeling what a recession
would feel like. Remember crypto is
further up the risk curve. It's going to
get hit first before other things get
hit. But then other industries don't
really feel that bad. Now what's also
interesting is like the AI. I mean yes
AI if you look at uh semis recently
there there was a a correction but so
what right? They're still up a lot. Um,
sometimes the biggest disconnect is
regionally.
And we actually have a lot of new charts
that I I'll show you some of them. But
regionally, if you're in the United
States, you might feel like you're in a
recession. If you're in parts of the
United States, and then other parts you
feel like things are great. Now, look at
what I'm talking about. If we look at a
map
of the number, a map of the states, the
United States, where the unemployment
rate has gone up over the last 6 months,
it's just kind of hit or miss. Like some
states has gone up, some states that
actually went down. To give you an idea
of what a recession would look like,
scroll this back to 2008. It's the whole
country. The market will always look for
a reason to go up, right? or it'll it'll
just go up, I should say. It's not
looking for a reason to go up. The
market will go up as long as there's
like a pocket of optimism somewhere.
It will climb the wall of worry because
it'll say, "Well, you know what? Yes, I
know that maybe this region of the
United States is doing poorly, but over
there they're doing great and so we're
going to keep climbing the wall of
worry." Where the recessions happen is
when there's no silver lining to
anything. Right now, there's still been
the silver lining, right? There's still
places that are doing okay. And if you
play this, right, if you just sort of
looked at 2021 22, there's pockets, but
there's always a spot, right? There's
always a few spots where it's okay.
There hasn't been a period in the last
several years where it was the entire
country. Not like what you saw back in
2008 and 2001 where it's literally the
entire country. So, we have to consider
that. Now if we if we count these up as
a function of time and look at the
number of states where the unemployment
rate is rising and we look at just over
over say the last 6 months you can see
that it's you know it's reached some
high levels but there's always been a
small pocket. You can see it never went
up to basically being the entire
country. I guess you could argue that in
1990 it wasn't the entire country, but
also guess what? In 1990, we had a 20%
correction in stocks. And you know, we
already had a 20% correction in stocks,
right? Back over here with the whole
tariff stuff. We had a 20% drop. That
20% drop quantitatively
is not necessarily any different than
the 20% drop we had in 1990. And by the
way, that actually did correspond to uh
a recession.
But you can see that it has not been the
whole country and so the market
continues to climb the wall of worry.
Now thinking about the unemployment
rate,
some of you are not from the United
States and you probably get somewhat
tired of me only ever talking about the
United States. We have started to add
some other regions as well. uh for
instance we can look at the unemployment
rate for various countries right so if
you want to look at various countries
you can look at the United States you
could then look at say like Japan uh
Canada New Zealand I'm going to New
Zealand uh next month so you can see the
New Zealand unemployment rate has been
trending up South Africa way up there
Switzerland a lot lower the UAE you've
got China Brazil and so on and so forth
Mexico, the Netherlands. What's really
interesting is we can average these out,
but I don't want to average them in a
way that weights them all the same. I
want to weight them by their GDP. So, if
we average out a lot of these different
countries, we might ignore a couple of
them just because we don't have the data
series going back far enough. You can
read the description here if you want to
pause the video and read it. If you
average them out and weight it by GDP,
you get a chart that looks like this
where the unemployment rate has been
slowly trending up, but it's kind of
stalled out recently and has been going
back down. That's why there's been this
discussion about are we going to get a
rate hike or not? On one hand, the
unemployment rate's been going down,
but on the other hand,
inflation
had gone back up some, right? Like
inflation had ticked back up recently.
It's pulled back some. There's still
this geopolitical conflict stuff going
on. It's hard to know what's going to
happen. If you look at a global
inflation rate map, we don't have it for
all the countries yet, but we can see we
have it for some. You know, it's still
relatively low in a lot of the different
um countries compared to where it was
back in say like 2022
when it got pretty bad. You can see that
things have cooled off, but inflation's
still not home as they say. like it's
still not necessarily back at that 2%
target. If you go back and look at some
of the other labor market statistics, um
you could go look at things like um the
unemployment duration and see that that
has been trending up, right? So things
are kind of getting worse, but it's very
slow and no one really knows like when
it's going to tip the iceberg and
actually really start to matter. If you
look at the unemployment, I want to look
at reason or let's actually look at the
youth unemployment rate. If you look at
the youth unemployment rate for the
United States,
you can see that that has been in an
uptrend, but that's actually a lot
higher. It's at 9%.
It's a lot different than what it is for
people that are a little bit older.
We could also look at the unemployment.
We sorry we looked at the unemployment
duration already, right? Like that's
been trending up. But I wanted to I
think it's under the other category.
It's the reason for unemployment. Um let
me just search it up here in the search
box. Reason
unemployment level by reason for
unemployment. You can see that if you're
if you're just looking at uh job losers,
it's kind of stalled out here. If you
look at job losers on temporary layoff,
that would actually picked back up a
little bit. Um, you can see permanent
job losers. Let's just select all of
them and then let's look to see which
ones are are highest. So, you can see
all the way up here job losers is is
highest. But you can also go through it
and see that some of them are from being
on temporary layoff. Some of them are
not temporary layoff.
793,000 were just from people leaving
their job.
Okay. So, in a lot of these categories,
it's actually stalled out recently and
has not continued that uptrend. But when
you think about the unemployment rate
going down, the reason the market is
somewhat confused is because non-farm
payroll was negative. Therefore, now the
market's not so convinced of a rate hike
in September. There's only about a 43.9%
chance as it stands right now that
you're going to get a rate hike in
September. You might, I mean, according
to the market, perhaps October or
December, but it has it sort of tilted
away from September. Obviously, there's
still another labor market report to go.
There's another inflation report to go.
So, a lot can change between now and
then. There's actually probably two
there might be two inflation reports to
go depending on the timing of it. Um, so
this though I was thinking about and we
cover the Fed a lot, right? And we'll
talk about, you know, interest rates and
and we'll talk about what the Fed's
doing. But if you look here at the
United States, obviously the Fed has
stalled out. But go through some of the
other ones. Look at Brazil
looks a little bit different, right?
They lowered rates and they raised rates
again. Look at the Euro area. They've
already started raising rates, right?
You can see that actually went back up a
little. Singapore, you can see the
easing cycle has sort of stalled. Look
at South Africa. Again, they raised
rates. Australia, rates have been going
back up. The UAE stalled out, not a rate
hike yet. South Korea, rates have
already been going back up. Canada
hasn't started yet. India hasn't
started. Japan, they they missed the
rate hiking cycle that a lot of other
countries went through in 2022 and 2023,
and now they're kind of raising rates
pretty late on. Mexico has been going
down. Actually, New Zealand, it looks
like New Zealand is starting to head
back up. And then you got the UK stalled
out. Uh, and then of course, China. Now
what I thought though is what if we do
the same thing. What if we calculate
interest rates GDP weighted? Now when
you do that it looks like this. You can
see that weighted interest rates stalled
out at around 4.6%. They then fell down
to about 3.4 but they've been slowly
trying to go back up. So the easing
cycle has stalled and it's arguably one
of the reasons why crypto has continued
to struggle throughout this midterm
year. if you need a narrative, but you
don't need one. But if you needed one,
it's right there for you.
So, it's a it's a really interesting
dilemma right now where the Fed doesn't
really want to make a mistake because we
already saw total non-farm payroll
year-over-year change is really close to
going negative. They don't want to hike
into an economy that's slowing down. The
problem is we don't know if the economy
is actually slowing down or not. I would
argue that it's not necessarily at this
moment. And one of the arguments for
that is if you look at interest rates in
the United States and if you kind of buy
my argument about the the neutral rate
and the 2-year yield, but if you look at
interest rates that are currently at
3.75%,
if you were to overlay the 2-year yield
onto that chart, what you'll notice
here,
let me pin this to the scale. What
you'll notice is that the 2-year yield
is now above the Fed funds rate. And a
lot of times the Fed funds rate will
chase the 2-year yield. So if this is
not to come back down quickly, then the
Fed might eventually have to chase this.
There is precedent for it, right? Like
we saw this happen in the '9s. If you go
look at the '9s, you can see that the
Fed funds rate was going up, it went
down. Um but then as the 2-year went
back up, we did get a rate hike. And
then and then we um the 2-year collapsed
in 98, went all the way back up. the the
Fed chased it for several months and
then we finally got the end of the
business cycle, but it took years to
play out, right? It took years.
So,
you know, and if you look, by the way,
if you look at interest rates in the if
you look at um interest rates in the
United States
and subtract out interest rates in
Japan,
what you'll see is that when this metric
drops quickly, it often will end with a
recession, which are these green lines.
We just haven't had it yet. Who knows
when it's going to be? My guess, as I've
said, within the next couple of years,
but doesn't necessarily have to mean
right now. In fact, we have a dashboard
to track it. We have a on the website if
you want to sign up, links in the
description below, we have a macro
recession risk dashboard. And if you
look at the summary risk, it shows you
that the risk of a recession over the
last four years or so has been
relatively low. Four to five years. Like
it's only gotten to like.16 risk. So, it
hasn't really elevated to the point of
calling for a recession. And again, it's
some it's often a fool's errand to call
for it. Yeah, I mean, we'll get one at
some point, but
a lot of money, more money is made, more
money is lost betting on crashes than
the actual crashes themselves. So, yes,
at the end of the business cycle, it
will likely all come uh to sort of a
sort of a climax, an ending to the
business cycle, but it it's clearly not
there yet. And until you start to see
initial claims head up, I've said
before, as long as initial claims are
below 300K, we're just not in a
recession. And it's kind of foolish to
say that you're in one when initial
claims are that low. When the
unemployment rate is turning down,
you're not in one, right? But when that
changes, then we'll talk about it. So,
we have this macro recession risk
dashboard. We also have a liquidity risk
dashboard that takes into account a lot
of different things um like policy
rates, yield, dollar strength, central
bank liquidity, and funding stress
proxies. You can see that things have
been relatively tight for a while, but
they can stay that way, right? And this
is one of the reasons why the blue chips
of the industry have been have been
doing much better than the than the
riskier plays is because people kind of
sense that there's this uncertainty and
and AI has been keeping the stock market
going for a while and it probably can
continue. Um, but people want to bet on
companies that they think will survive.
And when you're in a business cycle
environment like the one we're in,
you people bet on the blue chips, right?
right? They bet on the blue chips a lot
sooner than they'll bet on on riskier
stuff. So, that's an important lesson I
think a lot of people learned this past
cycle. It's one of the reasons why we've
been tracking Bitcoin dominance where
the entire cycle. And by the way, I know
some people say, you know, Ben's not
talking about Bitcoin dominance because
it's gone down. But guys, first of all,
I never said it was going to go up
forever. But second of all, if you
exclude stable coins, it's still going
up, right? Just because if you include
stable coins, it's dropped. But look, if
you exclude stables, Bitcoin dominance
is still going up. In fact, it's almost
near where it was back late last year.
The only reason it's dropped is because
stable coin dominance went up. So,
there's a lot of interesting things
going on in the market right now, right?
For the S&P, my guess is that the
strength will likely continue for a
little bit longer, but I would look for
a correction to start by late September
at the latest in line with prior midterm
years, 2014, 2018, 2022. A majority of
those years had corrections that started
in September and then they continued on
into October. One of those midterm
years, it started in August. But I got
to believe that it's going to it's going
to play out in the same way in the same
way that it it usually does. And when
you look at the Fed, the next Fed
meeting is September 16th. So, you know,
maybe they don't raise rates and the
bond market revolts or maybe they do
raise rates and people get nervous that
the easing cycle is over. I don't know
what the narrative is going to be, but
oftentimes around midepptember, uh,
you'll start to see a correction over in
the stock market. So, we still might
have, you know, several weeks before we
see that um play out. But those are my
views. And again, we've got all these
different charts on the website, all
these macro charts that you can look at
and and track and and see what's going
on. So, in in in a lot of ways, we've
expanded it. If you want to check it out
and see what's going on in uh sort of
your region of the world, you can try
and do that. But again, if you guys like
the content, subscribe, give the video a
thumbs up, check out the sale on the
platform. You can find that to the link
in the description below into the
cryptoverse.com. And finally, if you
want to come do this in person, come
listen to uh some people speak about
these charts. I'll be speaking at the
ITC conference in November. Make sure
you get your ticket. Prices are going up
on September 1st. Uh the conference will
take place in late November. Thank you
guys for tuning in. Subscribe. I'll see
you guys next time. Bye.